asses aimed to detect or quantify the
presence of a particular molecular
target and that is done by measuring how
a test molecule binds to it there are
many different types of RC this
presentation focuses on radio ligand
binding asses but the principles
described are equally applicable to
immunoassays where an antibody binds to
the protein of interest in both cases it
is binding to the target or the specific
binding that is of interest but
chemicals can interact in a less
specific way with other sites present in
the reaction mixture that binding is
known as nonspecific binding it is
important to realize that the total
amount of binding that's detected in an
assay is the sum of the specific and the
nonspecific binding so methods are
needed to separate the specific binding
from the nonspecific binding this
diagram illustrates the binding sites on
a cell membrane that are available to a
ligand by definition ligands bind to
receptors with high affinity this means
that they bind tightly much tighter than
to other sites in the cell so this shows
specificity for the receptor ligand
binding assays usually employ
preparations that contain only one type
of receptor to which the ligand binds
with high affinity the preparation will
therefore contain a limited or a finite
number of these receptors nonspecific
sites are any other site that the ligand
can interact with since these sites lack
the key structural requirements of the
receptor for binding the ligand will
interact loosely with these sites low
affinity binding can take place with a
wide variety of molecules so nonspecific
binding can involve many different sites
indicated here by different colored
diamonds so we are now going to add a
radio labeled ligand also known as a hot
ligand
when added to a solution ligand
molecules move around randomly and
continuously as ligand molecules come
into contact with the specific binding
sites they may interact and dwell there
for a short time before leaving and
moving around again so ligand molecules
constantly bind and unbind a move away
again once the hot ligand has been added
to the solution the system gradually
reaches equilibrium when the number of
ligand molecules binding at any one time
is equal to the number unbinding binding
at equilibrium is described by the
equation shown here where L is the
ligand R is the receptor and L R is the
ligand receptor complex k plus 1 and k
minus 1 are the rate constants governing
the binding reaction
the approach to equilibrium can be
followed experimentally by stopping the
assay at various intervals after adding
the hot ligand and measuring the amount
of radioactive ligand that has bound to
the tissue or receptor sample at each
time point
the results of such an experiment are
then plotted the time after adding the
hot ligand is plotted on the x-axis and
the radioactivity measured from the
tissue containing the receptors is on
the y-axis the measurements made at each
time are plotted individually as more
hot ligand binds to the receptors the
number of radioactive counts increases
this shows that over several minutes
binding gradually increases until it
reaches a steady equilibrium now let's
see what happens when you add more of
the ligand but this time we will add
cold ligand the cold ligand is exactly
the same as the hot ligand except that
it doesn't have the radio label in
addition we will add a lot more of the
cold ligand than there is hot they can't
there's quite a lot going on here so we
will focus in on the receptors and
ligands at the top of the cell
as with the hot ligand the cold ligand
molecules also move around constantly
when a cold ligand encounters an empty
receptor it will bind in the same way
that the hot ligand does and as hot
ligands vacate receptors their place can
be taken back old ligand importantly
because there is much more cold ligand
than hot ligand at equilibrium
most of the receptors will be occupied
by the cold ligand in other words the
hot ligand is displaced by excess cold
ligand
so now let's look at other binding sites
that ligands can interact with
nonspecific binding is law affinity the
ligand only binds loosely but because
they're low affinity there are lots of
these sites available until now I've
Illustrated binding to receptors on a
cell but many binding experiments use
homogenized tissues and membranes so as
well as binding sites on the
extracellular surface of the membrane
there may be intracellular sites
available incubations are carried out in
solution in some kind of test tube or
chamber and there may even be
nonspecific sites on the surface of the
container the main thing to remember
about nonspecific sites is that there
are lots of them probably with many
different structures to make things
clearer I'm now going to remove the
receptor sites from the diagram now we
will add the hot ligand again the ligand
molecules move around and interact with
nonspecific sites as they encounter them
just at the same way as they interact
with the specific sites but this time
they bind much more loosely let's see
what happens this time when we add an
excess of coke ligand hot and cold
ligands move around and interact with
the nonspecific sites as they encounter
them but this time there are enough
sites for the cord ligand to occupy
without having to compete with the hot
ligand so the hot ligand is not
displaced
so we can repeat the binding experiment
this time in the presence of an excess
of cold ligand to displace the specific
binding of the hot ligand in these
conditions the amount of radioactivity
measured from the tissue at each time
point represents the nonspecific binding
and is law in comparison to the total
binding the specific binding are binding
to the receptor can then be calculated
by subtracting the nonspecific binding
at each time point from the total
binding binding experiments can be
carried out using different
concentrations of the hot ligand the
amount of specific binding radioactivity
measured equilibrium is then recorded
for each concentration of hot ligand and
a binding curve constructed
according to the law of mass action the
rate of the binding reaction is
proportional to the product of the
concentrations of the receptor and the
ligand so as the concentration of ligand
is increased the equilibrium shifts to
the right and more and more of the
receptors are bound with ligand at any
time
so when measurements of specific binding
are plotted as a function of the
concentration of the radio labeled
ligand there is a hyperbolic increase in
specific binding until the receptors are
saturated and no more sites are
available for binding this is therefore
known as a saturation plot from this
plot you can obtain measurements of
binding affinity the relative rate
constants governing the forward and
backward reactions give this information
the ratio of k plus 1 or the forward
reaction over k minus 1 gives the
association or affinity constant but the
inverse measure K minus 1 over k plus 1
or the dissociation constant is the more
commonly used measurement the
dissociation constant can be easily
measured from the saturation curve
because it is equal to the ligand
concentration at which half of the
receptors or the specific sites are
bound with ligand this value can be
obtained by drawing a horizontal line at
50% of the maximum specific binding then
reading off the ligand concentration at
which that line meets the saturation
curve a low dissociation constant
indicates that a low concentration of
ligand is needed to bind 50% of the
receptors so a low dissociation constant
therefore indicates high affinity